Thomas Gray Manuscripts:
Thomas Gray Archive
- Poems, [ca. 1725]-1771; mss.poems
  - [Ode on the Pleasure Arising from Vicissitude], Now the golden Morn aloft; 1775; poems.oopv
    - Ode On the Pleasure arising from Vicissitude, 1780[?]; mss.0232; poems.oopv; 11 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode On the Pleasure arising from Vicissitude (p. 7) (Ode. II. [p. 9]). The poem, which is annotated "N.B. This Ode was left unfinished by Mr. Gray; but was compleated by Mr. Mason. // The lines by Mr. Mason are marked * / single words _" and is identical to the version in Mason's Poems ( 1775 ), 78-81, is part of a section called Fragments, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 19), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - [untitled], mss.0259; poems.oopv; 1 transcript, partial; HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36727>
      Transcript of the poem, partial, beginning "The common sun, the air, the skies", in the Amy Lowell Collection of Manuscripts of literary and musical figures, collected by American poet Amy Lowell.
    - Ode on the pleasure arising from vicissitude, 1799; mss.0272; poems.oopv; [?] transcript in the hand of Thomas Binns 200mm x 170mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 561, item N0507
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10643>
      Transcript in the hand of Thomas Binns, entitled Ode on the pleasure arising from vicissitude, in his autograph Miscellaneous manuscripts, vol. 4, a manuscript of a collection of about 100 primarily elegiac or sentimental poems.
  - Ode on the Spring, Lo! where the rosy-bosomed Hours; 1748; poems.oots
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 3-4
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 47-53
    Written at Stoke Poges early in June 1742 and sent in a letter, [c. 3 June 1742], to Richard West who was then dead. The letter was returned unopened and does not survive. First published, anonymously, in Dodsley's Collection of Poems by Several Hands, 3 vols, vol. II. (London, 1748 ), 265-267, reprinted in 6 vols, vol. II. (London, 1758 and later edns.), 325-327.
    - [untitled], [1742?]; mss.0116; poems.oots; 1 autograph, revised, partial [ll. 3-4]; YALE
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 97, 88, written on a leaf of random notes, item GrT 206, 100
      Jones, Thomas Gray, Scholar (1937), "Register of Gray Autograph Manuscripts", VI. 5, 178
      Autograph fragment, revised, of ll. 3-4, here untitled and beginning "Disclosed the breathing flowers", on a leaf of random notes.
    - [untitled], [1742?]; mss.0117; poems.oots; [2?] autograph draft written in ink and red pencil, partial [ll. 11-36, 43-50]; YALE
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 98, 88-89, on same leaf as item GrT 215, 101
      Autograph draft fragment, ll. 11-20 (in ink, second half of each line only), 21-36 (in red pencil, second half of each line only), 43-50 (in red pencil, first half of each line only), annotated "This was the original manuscript copy of Gray's Ode found amongst his papers by W. Mason who gave it to me E. Harcourt".
    - Noon-Tide, An Ode, beginning of June 1742; mss.0118; poems.oots; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 99, 89
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled Noon-Tide, An Ode, and beginning "Lo, where the rosie-bosom'd Hours", annotated "at Stoke, the beginning of June, 1742. sent to Fav: not knowing he was then Dead", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 275 and continued on p. 278.
    - [untitled], 20 October [1746]; mss.0119; poems.oots; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 100, 89
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 125, vol. i, 249-252 (subscription required)
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled, in a letter to Horace Walpole, 20 October [1746].
    - [untitled], [1?] February 1768; mss.0120; poems.oots; 1 autograph, partial [notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 101, 89
      Autograph notes to the poem, untitled but numbered 1. and identified on f. 3r as "1. Ode. (Lo, where the rosy-bosom'd &c:)" in MS instructions to Dodsley for the 1768 London edition, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768. The notes were first published in the poem's version in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0121; poems.oots; [1?] autograph, partial [notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 102, 89
      Autograph notes to the poem in MS instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
    - Ode on the Spring, 1780[?]; mss.0216; poems.oots; 7 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode on the Spring (p. 1) (Ode. I. [p. 3]). The poem is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - [untitled], [before 1860]; mss.0250; poems.oots; 4 transcript (lines 1-7, 11-50) in the hand of George Hamilton-Gordon c. 190 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/07/2010.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=107683>
      Transcript (lines 1-7, 11-50) in the hand of George Gordon, afterwards (1818) Hamilton-Gordon, 4th Earl of Aberdeen, K.G., K.T., Prime Minister (b. 1784, d. 1860) in his Aberdeen Papers, Vol. CCCIX (ff. 210) Miscellaneous papers, section 2 "Miscellaneous English occasional verse, centring chiefly round George, 4th Earl of Aberdeen, and the circle of visitors he met at Bentley Priory, Stanmore, the home of his father-in-law, John James Hamilton, 1st Marquess of Abercorn, which became his own residence for many years", item q "Poem, beg. 'Lo! Where the rosy-bosom'd hours', ff. 51-52b".
    - Lines, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0115; poems.oots; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 3-4] 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript of ll. 3-4, in the hand of John Mitford, possibly transcribed from one of the autograph MSS., in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 181r.
    - Lines, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0206; poems.oots; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 3-4] and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript of ll. 3-4, in the hand of John Mitford (crossed out), possibly transcribed from one of the autograph MSS., in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 29r.
  - Ode to Adversity, Daughter of Jove, relentless power; 1753; poems.otad
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 10-11
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 68-74
    Completed at Stoke Poges by August 1742 and sent in a letter to Horace Walpole, 8 September [1751]. First published, as Hymn to Adversity, in Dodsley's Designs ( 1753 ), [24].
    - Ode. To Adversity, August 1742; mss.0122; poems.otad; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 103, 89
      Autograph fair copy, revised, here entitled Ode. To Adversity and annotated "at Stoke, Aug. 1742", including two mottoes in Greek from Aeschylus, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 284-285.
    - Hymn to Adversity, 8 September [1751]; mss.0123; poems.otad; [2?] autograph fair copy, crossed out; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 104, 89
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 161, vol. i, 346-350 (subscription required)
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled Hymn to Adversity (crossed out), in a letter to Horace Walpole, 8 September [1751].
    - [untitled], [1?] February 1768; mss.0124; poems.otad; 1 autograph, partial [motto only] 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 105, 89
      Autograph motto for the poem, untitled but numbered 4. and identified on f. 3r as "4. Ode, to Adversity", in MS instructions to Dodsley for the 1768 London edition, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768. The motto first appeared in the poem's version in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0125; poems.otad; [1?] autograph, partial [motto only] 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 106, 89
      Autograph motto for the poem in MS instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
    - Ode to Adversity, 1780[?]; mss.0219; poems.otad; 7 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode to Adversity (p. 25) (Ode. IV. [p. 27]). The poem, which includes the motto in Greek and attribution on the title page, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - Hymn to Adversity. By Mr Gray., 1755[?]; mss.0242; poems.otad; 3 transcript in an unidentified hand 152 mm x 90 mm; BDLN; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in the SCRR at the RSL, Bodleian Library, on 11/03/2010.
      Crum (ed.), First-Line Index (1969), vol. I, 185, item D41
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=65390>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, in six numbered stanzas, in a volume containing extracts and notes, many relating to grammar and language, with copies of verse, in several hands, mainly from printed sources, 18th cent., inscribed Miscellanies and signed "Rob: Trail" (Summary Catalogue, 45980).
    - Hymn to adversity, [between 1768 and 1769]; mss.0268; poems.otad; [?] transcript 190mm x 130mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 175, item D0034
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10635>
      Transcript, entitled Hymn to adversity, in a Commonplace book entitled Amusements 1768-69, a manuscript, in two hands, of a collection of several dozen primarily serious poems and poetical extracts, many on moral and elegiac subjects.
    - Hymn to adversity, [between 1766 and 1800]; mss.0269; poems.otad; [?] transcript in the hand of James Forbes; YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10637>
      Transcript, entitled Hymn to adversity, in James Forbes' Commonplace book, 1766-1800, vol. I "Poems on Several Occasions Collected from Different Authors", a manuscript collection of approximately 150 poems and excerpts, primarily epitaphs and elegies, poems in praise of virtues, odes dedicated to women, and poems on nature and weather.
  - [Oh ubi colles], Oh ubi colles, ubi Faesularum; 1890; poems.lt20
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 152 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 318 (with English prose translation)
    Written probably at London soon after returning from the Grand Tour, in [September] 1741. First published, untitled, in
    Tovey (ed.), Gray and his Friends (1890), 296
    - [untitled], [1741?]; mss.0126; poems.lt20; 1 autograph, revised; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 107, 89
      Autograph, revised, here untitled, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 381.
  - On L[or]d H[olland']s Seat near M[argat]e, K[en]t, Old and abandoned by each venal friend; 1769; poems.oxst
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 53
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 259-264
    Written while on a visit to William Robinson in Denton, Kent, in June 1768. First published, anonymously without Gray's consent, as Inscription for the Villa of a decay'd Satesman [sic] on the Sea-Coast, in The New Foundling Hospital for Wit (London, 1769 ) iii. 34-35.
    - On L.d H--ds Seat near M--e. K.t, [before 1794]; mss.0130; poems.oxst; 2 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton 198 mm x 161 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 108, 89
      Transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton, beginning "Old and abandon'd by each venal friend".
    - On seeing the Seat of a decayed Nobleman in Kent, 1 May 1777; mss.0131; poems.oxst; 1 transcript, revised and annotated, in the hand of William Cole 325 mm x 220 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 109, 89
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=109944>
      Transcript, revised and annotated, in the hand of William Cole, in a volume entitled Cambridgeshire Collections, Vol. XX, bequeathed by Rev. W. Cole. The transcript is here entitled On seeing the Seat of a decayed Nobleman in Kent and beginning "Old & abandon'd by its venal Friend", annotated "These Verses on Lord Holland, are said to have been composed by Mr. Gray: Dr Glynn dictated them to me at Milton May 1. 1777."
    - On Lord Holland's seat at Kingsgate, [after 1804?]; mss.0127; poems.oxst; 2 transcript in an unidentified hand 198 mm x 159 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 89
      Transcript, entitled On Lord Holland's seat at Kingsgate. By Mr. Gray in an unidentified hand, in a volume entitled Twining Papers, vol. VIII "Miscellaneous".
    - [untitled], [after 1769]; mss.0207; poems.oxst; 2 transcript in an unidentified hand 220 mm x 177 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=137055>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand in the form of six numbered stanzas, untitled, but headed "The following Stanzas were written by Mr. Gray at Kingsgate in Kent, the Seat of Lord Holland", in a volume entitled Eighteenth Century Verse.
    - On Lord Holland's Marine Villa at Kingsgate, by Mr Gray, [between 1771 and 1806]; mss.0128; poems.oxst; 1 transcript; HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=55640> (no author attribution)
      Transcript of the poem in Charlotte Anne Hester Burney's (who became Mrs. Francis, and afterwards married Ralph Broome) verse Commonplace book ( 1771 - 1806 ), 116-118.
    - [?], [1782?]; mss.0129; poems.oxst; [?] transcript in an unidentified hand; LGLT
    - Inscription for a villa of a decayed statesman on the sea coast, [after 1805]; mss.0237; poems.oxst; 2 transcript in an unidentified hand on a "leaf watermarked 1805"; LELI
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=3707>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, beginning "Old and abandon'd by each venal friend", on a "leaf watermarked 1805 inserted in a scrapbook of miscellaneous original and transcribed poems written out from c.1750 to the twentieth century".
    - On Lord Holland [...] at Kingsgate near Margate, 1769[?]; mss.0244; poems.oxst; 2 transcript in an unidentified hand 220 mm x 162 mm; BDLN; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in the SCRR at the RSL, Bodleian Library, on 11/03/2010.
      Crum (ed.), First-Line Index (1969), vol. II, 681, item O1000
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=77210>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, in six numbered stanzas, in a volume entitled Memorials of Richard Gough, volume II, section I. "Poems preserved by Richard Gough Esq.". The poem is listed with the date "1769" in the table of contents on fol. 7 of the volume. The volume, which is 14 5/8 x 9 3/4 in. in size and contains 320 leaves, is one of two Volumes of Poems and other interesting Memorials of Richard Gough, Esq., F.R.S., F.S.A.., collected by J[ohn] B[owyer] Nichols (Summary Catalogue, 32551).
    - On the seat of a decayed nobleman in the Isle of Thanet, mss.0273; poems.oxst; [?] transcript; YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 608, item O0840
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10645>
      Transcript entitled On the seat of a decayed nobleman in the Isle of Thanet.
  - [Orders of Insects], Alas lorica tectas Coleoptera jactant.; 1814 and 1966; poems.lt21
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 179-185 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 337-342 (with English prose translation)
    Begun not earlier than 1759, the year Gray bought his copy of Linnaeus, but possibly only in the last years of his life. The additional lines were presumably abandoned due to his last illness in 1771. First published, as Generick Characters of the Orders of Insects, and of the Genera of the first six Orders, named Coleoptera, Hemiptera, Lepidoptera, Neuroptera, Hymenoptera, and Diptera; expressed in Technical Verses, in
    Mathias (ed.), Works (1814), vol. II, 570-573
    . Additional lines ("Palpos ore duos, triplexque Lepisma flagellum") first published in
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 185
    - [untitled], [after 1759]; mss.0132; poems.lt21; [?] autograph fair copy; HARV
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 110, 90, in an interleaved copy of Linnaeus, Systema Naturae, 10th rev. ed. (Holmiae, 1758-59), item GrT 334, 113
      Autograph fair copy, untitled, in an interleaved copy of Linnaeus, Systema naturae per regna tria naturae, secundum classes, ordines, genera, species, cum charateribus, differentiis, synonymis, locis ..., 10th rev. ed. (Holmiae, 1758-59).
    - [untitled], [after 1759]; mss.0133; poems.lt21; 1 autograph fragment, revised, additional lines; MOLI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 4, 79, together with a list of books, item GrT 178, 97, cf. item GrT 233, 102
      Jones, Thomas Gray, Scholar (1937), "Register of Gray Autograph Manuscripts", VI. 20(d), 181
      Autograph fragment, revised, here untitled, five additional lines on one page, together with a list of books, later tipped(?) into Herbert Paul, Queen Anne (Asnières, 1906).
  - [Paraphrase of Psalm LXXXIV], Oh! Tecta, mentis dulcis amor meae!; 1849 and 1890; poems.lt22
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 112-114 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 285-287 (with English prose translation)
    Written probably as a school exercise at Eton between 1725 and 1734, possibly Gray's earliest complete composition. First published, ll. 1-20 only, in The Gentleman's Magazine N.S. 32 (October 1849), 343, published in full, as Early Alcaics of Gray, in
    Tovey (ed.), Gray and his Friends (1890), 300-301
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0134; poems.lt22; 2 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 111, 90
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford, untitled, subscribed "The above is the 84th Psalm" and "[N.B. The above Ode is written in Mr Grays Hand: but evidently when young, the hand being unformed, & like a Schoolboys, tho' very plain & careful. The Leaf on which it is written, apparently torn from a Copy-book. Some of the Expressions resemble those in the Gr. Chartreuse Ode.]", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 67-68.
  - [Parody on an Epitaph], Now clean, now hideous, mellow now, now gruff; 1882; poems.pare
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 256-257
    Composed shortly after visiting the church at Appleby, c. 3 September 1767, while on a short tour of the Lake District with Thomas Wharton. First published, untitled, in
    Gosse, Gray (1882), 176
    - [untitled], [1767]; mss.0136; poems.pare; 1 autograph fair copy 63 mm x 197 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 112, 90
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled, on a slip of paper annotated in the hand of Thomas Wharton "Extempore Epitaph on Ann Countess of Dorset, Pembroke, and Montgomery, made by Mr. Gray on reading the Epitaph on her mothers tomb in the Church at Appleby composed by the Countess, in the same manner."
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0135; poems.pare; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [2 lines] 162 mm x 101 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 90
      Transcript, untitled but headed "Grays MSS (in Masons collection)", of a 2-line version beginning "She swept, she hissd, grew mellow & lookd gruff", in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 1.
  - The Progress of Poesy. A Pindaric Ode, Awake, Aeolian lyre, awake; 1757; poems.pppo
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 12-17
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 155-177
    Begun not earlier than September 1751 and completed by December 1754 when Gray sent the poem in a letter to Thomas Wharton, dated 26 December 1754. First published, as Ode. in Odes by Mr. Gray ( 1757 ), 5.
    - Ode, in the Greek manner, [1754?]; mss.0138; poems.pppo; 2 autograph, revised; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 114, 90
      Martin, Chronologie (1931), 145
      Autograph, revised, here entitled Ode, in the Greek manner, the first line altered from "Awake my Lyre, my Glory, wake" to the first line as published, including an alternative version of five of the last six lines, and annotated "Finish'd in 1754. printed together with the Bard, an Ode. Aug: 8. 1757", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. II, 727-728.
    - Ode, in the Greek Manner, 26 December 1754; mss.0139; poems.pppo; 4 autograph fair copy 240 mm x 191 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 115, 90